Muhammad Ahmad Bashir (Curriculum Vitae)

Postdoctoral Research Fellow International Computer Science Institute (ICSI) 1947 Center Street, Ste. 600, Berkeley, CA 94704

mahmad@icsi.berkeley.edu
https://ahmadbashir.com

Research Interests

My current research focuses on **web/mobile security & privacy**. In particular, I am studying the **online advertising** ecosystem to understand how it impacts users' privacy. My goal is to make the online advertising ecosystem more transparent to enable users make informed decisions regarding their personal information. I have previously worked on projects aimed at **limiting abuse** on online services such as Facebook and Twitter.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science	Aug 2014 – Aug 2019
Northeastern University	
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science	Sep 2008 – May 2012
LUMS School of Science and Engineering	-

Employment History

1. Postdoctoral Research Fellow (ICSI, Berkeley)	Oct 2019 – Present
2. Graduate Research Assistant (Northeastern University)	Sep 2014 – Aug 2019
3. Research Intern (ICSI, Berkeley)	Summer 2018
4. Security Engineering Intern (Threat Infrastructure, Facebook Inc.)	Summer 2017
5. Security Engineering Intern (Online Safety, Facebook Inc.)	Summer 2016
6. Research Intern (Max Planck Institute, SWS)	Oct 2012 – Jan 2013
7. Research Assistant (LUMS-SSE)	Jun 2011– Sep 2011/ Feb 2013– Jul 2013

Honors and Awards

1. Best Stupent Paper Award (FPF Privacy Papers for Policymakers)	2018
2. Best Paper Award (COSN '15)	2015
3. Best Paper Award (SECRYPT '15)	2015
4. Research Intern Fellowship (Max Planck Institute for Software Systems)	2012
5. Winner, Ericsson – PTA Mobile Excellence Award (National award)	2011
6. Winner, SOFTEC (National award)	2011

Teaching Experience

1. Teaching Assistant (CS 3700 - Networks and Distributed Systems)	Fall 2018
2. Teaching Assistant / Guest Lecturer (CS 2550 - Foundations of Cybersecurity)	Spring 2018
3. Teaching Assistant (CS 585: Service Oriented Computing)	Spring 2013
4. Teaching Assistant (CS 582: Distributed Systems)	Fall 2012
5. Teaching Assistant (CS 380: Databases)	Spring 2012

Muhammad Ahmad Bashir 2

Selected Publications

- 1. A Longitudinal Analysis of the ads.txt Standard (IMC '19)
 - A 15-month long study analyzing the adoption of the ads.txt standard by Alexa-100K websites.
- 2. Quantity vs. Quality: Evaluating User Interest Profiles Using Ad Preference Managers (NDSS '19)
 - First large-scale study of the "interests" inferred by ad networks using Ad Preference Managers.
 - We investigate how these interests were inferred and how useful they were according to the users.
- 3. How Tracking Companies Circumvented Ad Blockers Using WebSockets (IMC '18 & ConPro '18')
 - A study of 100,000 websites to investigate how some tracking companies leveraged a bug in the webRequest
 API to circumvent blocking extensions for tracking and serving ads using WebSockets.
- 4. Diffusion of User Tracking Data in the Online Advertising Ecosystem (PETS '18) [FPF Privacy Papers for Policy Makers Award]
 - We model how user tracking data propagates in the advertising ecosystem because of RTB.
 - We model the efficacy of ad and tracker blocking extensions at protecting users' privacy.
- 5. Recommended For You: A First Look at Content Recommendation Networks (IMC '16)
 - First look at how content (ads and recommendations) is served by Content Recommendation Networks.
 - This study highlights the inconsistencies in how the content is served and calls for stronger regulations.
- 6. Tracing Information Flows Between Ad Exchanges Using Retargeted Ads (USENIX Security '16)
 - We detect information sharing among ad exchanges using a generic technique involving retargeted ads.
 - This study detects 31% of cookie matching partners which were missed by prior methods.
- 7. Strength in Numbers: Robust Tamper Detection in Crowd Computations (COSN '15) [Best Paper]
 - Detection of large-scale (Sybil-tampered) crowd computations in Online Social Networks.
 - Dataset consists of roughly 300M Twitter users and 30K businesses with 341K reviews from Yelp.
- 8. Towards Detecting Anomalous User Behavior in Online Social Networks (USENIX Security '14)
 - Detection of anomalous identities, using PCA, on Facebook used in diverse attack strategies.

Ongoing Work

- 1. Cross Device Tracking
 - A comprehensie study of the state of cross-device tracking and the underlying mechanisms used.
 - High-level idea is to construct several personas, perform browsing, and solicit ads on other devices.
- 2. SDKs & Android Permissions
 - A methodological way of examining which SDK requested which Android perimssion.

Technical Skills

Languagues: Python, Java, Hack, C++, Javascript, SQL, HTML, PHP

Tools: Spark, Weka, Matlab, BPEL **Platforms:** Linux, Windows, Mac OS X

References

Available upon request